let's go to Aran theer you guys
ready I told the AI to
show a confused guy in the
dark and he did pretty good my AI is
like a 60% AI it's artificial
intelligence and artificial idiot he
mixed together but uh anyway
Nar finally says are you done
criticizing me about emptiness and why
emptiness means there cannot be the four
higher truth and all those other things
are are you finished the GU says yeah I
think I covered everything you're not a
Buddhist okay and then uh ARA gar
says if you think emptiness means those
things then you don't get get the
purpose and you don't get the essence
and you don't get the point of emptiness
you don't get the purpose you don't get
the essence and you don't get the point
of emptiness
okay and then the rest of the chapter
he's explaining things but I thought
since you guys have nothing to do
today you could figure out these three
or I'd like to hear tomorrow
your opinion of what are these three
okay what's when the gist says you don't
understand the purpose of emptiness and
you don't understand the essence of
emptiness and you don't understand the
point of emptiness and and
point how does that differ from
Essence uh I'd like to see what you
think by the way we don't have
any commentary by AR
okay we have Chand kti 4 or 500 years
later we have
jetona
but we don't know exactly what he meant
and I'm I'm uh I'm curious what you guys
think okay so maybe uh cooking today in
your retreat cabin Retreat cabin is for
cooking here right here okay so cook it
in your retreat and and let let let's
talk about it tomorrow okay we have
class to no we don't have this class
tomorrow oh Tuesday we have okay
tomorrow we have two translation classes
okay sometimes the organizer of the
where I'm giving a teaching they say
could you just move the two classes and
I say no they are part of every program
so if you want to irritate grandpa say
why don't you just move it
okay and I say move your
program okay all right it's part of
every program I
think and
anyway all right uh let's get to the
next yeah in fact
uh I get my deepest questions in the boy
bathroom that you know I'm trying to do
my work
and people always ask I can't go
anywhere they're asking me
questions uh so I got this question just
now in the boy bathroom and if you're
the person who asked me the question now
you now is my answer okay and I told you
it was
coming okay so
um basically this verse says when the
Buddhas
teach the Dharma they use both
realities the what are the two realities
the deceptive reality of the world and
the reality which is Ultimate okay two
two
realities and it
means
uh Buddha needs both realities okay like
you can't say oh Buddha just spends all
their time in emptiness you know it's
it's not the case they also need
apparent reality or normal reality they
they use normal reality and they use
Ultimate Reality and they they have to
balance them and and we have to balance
them and the person in the
bathroom about normal reality in the
sense
of earning a
living and
it's so frustrating that I can't just
sit and think about emptiness all day
you know I'm also have to make money you
know and I think Aran NE Guardian is
answering that comment in this verse
this is verse number eight of the 24th
chapter and he says look you need both
okay you need both and I think we all
have seen the
extreme of someone who just uses normal
reality they just make money they just
work hard they just raise a family they
just have kids and then that's all they
do and then it fails because of
impermanence it fails the kids grow up
or the kids pass away the job fails the
business fails
or what's worse if you're successful and
then you die like you know there's no
future to those things they must fail
they must uh cause problems they must
they have to that's their nature that's
that's normal reality and then on the
other hand you have doing retreat at
Diamond Mountain you have studying
emptiness studying the classics sitting
in one of your five houses you know you
have this other side of things and the
guardian says you cannot have the second
without the
first okay you have to have a life and
then you can make that life amazing but
don't think you can just make life
amazing without a life okay and it's
very beautiful you know and I've had
some students
insist my teacher had a student okay I
not only had 50 years of suffering with
my own students but I suffered with his
students for 25 years and I saw many
many so there is a guy he heard about
renunciation he heard
L and he said he came to my teacher he
said I'm gonna live like millera you
know and my teacher is like oh really
you know and he said yeah no more of
this you know
working I'm gonna just live like mil
free like Miller ire you know and my
teacher's like and then uh this guy so
we lived in New Jersey we lived in a
small town and there was a small Forest
uh next to the
town and uh and he said I'm gonna go
live in the forest you know and and my
teacher is like well you know it is
Autumn in New Jersey and uh you know
we're headed towards winter in New
Jersey and before before global warming
we used to get this stuff called snow
and uh and I'm talking four feet 5 feet
of snow and he's like you know I'm gonna
go stand in the forest my teach okay you
know he said I'm I'm giving up this
working and impermanence and having a
family and all this normal stuff I'm
going to go to the forest you know my
teach okay yeah okay I'll see you later
then like two weeks later he came back
and he's like he sit down at the kitchen
table and eat everything in the
refrigerator and you know he's like that
Forest you know they don't have
refrigerators you know we're like yeah
you know and refrigerators they come
from a thing called money and that comes
from a thing called working you know and
he's like oh you know and uh you know
you need both the guardian of here is
saying you need both you need normal
reality and you need ultimate reality
and in fact they support each other in
fact they they go to hand in hand okay
have a nice job get a nice
income uh don't go crazy don't work 18
hour days you
know every job in the universe creates
something that people want that's why
they pay you and then that helps people
if you build houses if you make refriger
ators if you build cars it helps people
you know my dad I thought he was this
terrible capitalist imperialist you know
because he was a builder he built
neighborhoods and uh I always was afraid
to introduce him to my teacher and then
finally one day did they had to meet
each other and um and I was embarrassed
you know my wife knows my dad she she
came and when she was 16 and spent time
with us and and um so anyway I'm I'm not
looking forward to this my dad the
capitalist meaning my teacher the Dharma
man you know and then uh they sat down
in the kitchen of the temple Mongolian
Temple and uh and my my teacher looks at
my dad and says I heard you are a big
businessman yeah and I heard you build
houses for people big neighborhoods
hundreds of houses
yes that is such cool Dharma you know
I'm like what and he's like that's such
a Dharma activity you're giving so many
families a place to stay you're such a
bodyy sapper you know I wish I could be
like you you know and I'm like what
what's going on you know and uh then
after that my dad said
before I was hoping you would become a
Christian priest but now I think it's a
good
thing and
uh so anyway uh in this verse Aran the
guardian says you need both okay you
need both and and the ultimate argument
that he gives here it's very
sexy he
says when Buddha taught you
emptiness in the Deer Park or wherever
Raj
bira vulture PE when he taught the heart
Sutra at vulture's Peak did he use words
did he write down anything did people
write down the heart Sutra yes that's
not Ultimate Reality that's deceptive
reality that's normal reality the books
the teachings the translations the
programs at
DM these are all normal reality you know
we're going to go over there and eat
normal food I
hope and you know somebody had to pay
for it and by the way the sponsor
who uh Student Center is Dr Woo very
very very very kind uh the first time I
met him he said is there anything you
need I said yeah I need a c interor and
he's like how much does that cost and
I'm like I don't know you always double
when you talk to a
sponsor so I said I think it it's I
thought 100,000 so I said 200,000 he
said okay I got it covered and I'm like
w and then we built it and it was 1.2
million uh and I had to go to him and
you
know so anyway he covered it and if you
ever meet him or take a class from him
and this week you should you should
thank him and uh we're very very
grateful yeah
yeah you want to hear
secret so I had to have a translator to
talk to him and there's this young lady
from Shaman who's living in gang
Joo and she said I'll translate and then
uh I start my thing oh we have we don't
have cafeteria then
she's she's crying you know and then the
sponsor's like you need more money you
need more money then I always took her
with me after
that Shia
[Applause]
Bing so anyway you need both you know
you need a construction company to make
the place
thank God those guys aren't Dharma
students you know they can count they
can build they can put the roof on okay
really a good Dharma student should be
both and that's what Arian Guardian is
saying in this verse okay you need both
there has to be a organization there has
to be buildings there has to be books
there has to be money to do Dharma you
they go together and that's what he's
saying in this in this and it doesn't
have to be uh business doesn't have to
be nasty business can
be time tra okay and and we talked about
it already you know business can be
Diamond way if you do business with the
right state of mind it's unbelievable
practice okay uh you just you have to
have that state of mind and you you
actually the two need each other the
what the guardian assess to his critic
critic
criticizer he says look uh you need what
we call deceptive reality deceptive
reality means normal reality you need
normal reality in order to study
Ultimate Reality you need both you have
to have both they go together who
invented that
Buddha okay not meard here he says the
Buddha when the Buddha teaches the
Dharma he needs both they need both
somebody got to pay for the air
conditioner you know okay you need both
he's he's saying it's very nice
okay
okay it's not what hang
on I'm
sorry let's try that one what's your
next picture you guys
yeah okay
good the Gina says you need a balance
between deceptive reality and Ultimate
Reality there has to be a balance okay I
like this thing what's it called a
teeter
totter
huh oh what's the other
one seaw yeah okay
anyway I don't know why they're hard to
find pictures but of in seesaw T yeah he
says and I'll quote his verse he says
without relying on terms okay words
without relying on Words you could never
reach Ultimate Reality words are the
ultimate deceptive reality okay uh they
are not Ultimate Reality okay they are
the ultimate cause and effect okay words
all right so he says without words you
couldn't reach Ultimate Reality uh and
without Ultimate Reality you can't reach
Nana okay without emptiness you can't
reach Nana and that's the the the
Tibetan language
says you can't teach the Dharma without
terms without words but words are not
Ultimate Reality they are deceptive
reality okay so you need deceptive
reality you
need you need fake reality to get to
real reality
[Music]
okay all
right but but what nard is he has a
famous famous
line where someone says tell me what you
really believe you know tell me what's
your real position and he says I believe
whatever Farmers believe
that's his famous famous uh quotation
Canadian treee Keepers or something
whatever they believe is what I believe
okay and it's very famous he says I
believe whatever Farmers believe no
farmer thinks you can get a tree without
a
seed right he said whatever they say I
say okay all right um next picture weird
picture I tried okay I really tried you
don't know how hard I try ask my wife
how hard I try half an hour negotiating
with the AI you know I want a lady
taking a jewel off the forehead of a
snake and the AI doesn't know what's
possible or impossible right they're
just supposed to do what you say and I
tried like 20 times and this is the best
I don't know what's the gloopy red thing
in her eye okay I'm sorry
am I going to spend an extra hour to
take it out
no okay uh
anyway here's the verse he says when
people disrespect emptiness when they
say Emptiness is stupid okay or I don't
see any point to emptiness you know like
how is it going to help you in your life
to think that something's empty okay
they say I don't understand so when they
talk talk bad about
emptiness uh th those of little wisdom
are ruined okay uh they are ruined
[Music]
okay and then he has an example and in
ancient times if you wanted
to uh in ancient times it was believed
that uh very poisonous snakes would have
a jewel here a red Jewel like a ruby or
something and uh he said people who
disrespect the idea of emptiness or who
try to study emptiness and don't
understand it are like people who go
looking for poisonous cobras to take the
jewel off their forehead and they end up
dying they end up getting bitten by the
Cobra and and everything n Aran n says
is deeper right there's always a deeper
meaning
uh and what he's saying is that uh the
study of emptiness is dangerous it's
like a cobra and and you can take the
emptiness out of it you can get
emptiness out
of you can pluck The Jewel from the by
the way why is the snake important for
him
particularly he's n Gina his name means
king of the snakes King of the cobras
okay uh so and by the
way uh shenan who walked for 17 years
through 51 countries of Asia to bring
the Buddhism to China in the tong cha
for the tong TI thong who wanted to kill
him and then wanted to give him a a
tower okay isn't that the way it goes
uh he he visited a great library in
South India I think it was John Brady's
previous life and uh like all or
something and and shensong visited Aran
neer's Library Aran thearer was a book
collector Aran thearer tried to
save the books of his time he was the
alll of his time and he had a great
library in South India so he thought it
was important to save the books and he
spent a lot of his life trying to save
the early the Early books the early
sutras were 700 years before him hard
Sutra Diamond color Sutra these are 700
years old by the time of Nar and he's
trying to save them he built a library
he's trying to save the books shenan
went there shenan came home with a
thousand books translated them that
became Chinese
Buddhism
and he heard there were some books
missing in this
world and anyone who has watched Lord of
the Rings knows that
smog the dragon they like shiny precious
things especially gold and diamonds and
stuff like that uh so when
dragons hear that there's something
valuable they will try to hoard it
they'll try to collect it and then they
sit on
it and make sure nobody uses it uh which
is what people do with money and uh so
anyway uh he heard that the dragons had
some
scriptures uh that that they took home
to their world and uh so he learned how
to speak to them and he he became the
master of them Master means Arjun the
great Bowman of the bhagabat Gita the
great arrow shooter so he became the
Great Master of the dragons and he
collected some of the Boro bomo some of
the president parita from these nagas
and he brought them back to this world
so he knows
about approaching a dangerous snake
thing to get the most precious Jewel out
of them he did it you understand so when
he mentions it here you got to know the
background okay and he says Emptiness is
like this Jewel on the dragon's forehead
and to approach a to approach a
poisonous snake is dangerous and they
there's a chance you will get bitten
right and then you got a think about
that why did a guarder
say well it doesn't take much thought
people who don't know what they're doing
go after emptiness they go to try to
learn emptiness from someone who doesn't
understand it and then they say close
your eyes hey hey
hey everything okay in Chinese it means
black black black in rock and roll andm
hey hey okay yeah but it
means you know just close your eyes and
think about nothing okay and then you
got bit you understand if you try to
learn emptiness from someone who doesn't
know what Emptiness is you will get bit
by the same emptiness which means what
what do you guess is bitten by by fake
emptiness what's it look like you spend
your whole life staring at a wall
in a monastery and trying to think of
nothing okay you spend your whole life
trying to empty your
mind okay and then then you got poison
it would have been better if you worked
in the gas
station your whole life than to sit and
stare at a wall and try to think about
nothing because that's ultimate waste of
human life they don't even pay you for
that at least in the gas station they
pay you right so
okay uh he says they get hurt and then
he gives another example of something
called uh vid Vidya in Sanskrit uh we
had it like
Dar uh medicine Buddha mantras okay and
he says people who use a Dary and don't
know what they're doing can get bitten
they can get bitten by the dony okay so
you have to I think it
was oh it was Juan Hassel mentioned
yesterday if if you're really interested
in medicine Buddha practice read for
goodness sake read the essay in the book
you just
got uh that explains how the Mantra
Works otherwise you'll get bitten by the
Mantra and and then you end up your
whole life you will die and and the the
people you're trying to help with the
mantra will get sicker and you know it
won't work okay I think worse than
disaster is when it doesn't work you
know to to die of cancer is one thing to
do mantras and then die of cancer that's
frustrating okay all right
okay anyway Arian the garist says you
need emptiness to understand mantras and
you need emptiness to and and getting
emptiness has to be done
wisely and carefully you don't ask a an
Arizona rattlesnake to give you the
Jewel on his forehead without some
careful
negotiation okay you will get hurt okay
all right all right so it's interesting
he's saying people who study emptiness
wrong the wrong way get
hurt it's
interesting you can imagine right
um let's see here I'm sorry I I have
uh 1,200 pages of notes and uh it's a
little
tricky that's
not hang
on
okay is it what's your next image you
guys H what number is it do you
know I'll tell you what number it
is hang
[Music]
on
okay
11 what's 6.10
okay here we
go yeah okay 6.1 hang
[Music]
on no
yeah
[Music]
okay this image okay I I always like to
because of DCI because I write the DCI
courses I like
to find modern images that represent
ancient images
okay and uh this
represents Lord Buddha's
hesitation to teach for seven weeks okay
after he got
enlightened uh he refused to teach for
seven weeks and
uh this that's what this picture
represents when you see this picture
it's like the professor sat down in the
classroom and wasn't wasn't comfortable
to teach yet okay and Arian gar
in his in this chapter he says uh Lord
Buddha was
aware
that if he didn't teach emptiness
carefully people would
misunderstand and and I'd say that in
the last thousand years more people have
misunderstood emptiness than who
understood emptiness I think so and you
know you can go to I I listen all the
time
you know I I hear things from strange
people who say oh emptiness means empty
your mind don't and try to think about
nothing you know uh nothing
matters you don't have to be kind to
people everything's empty anyway like
that and uh why do you think this
picture relates to
that
huh say
again well yeah it means uh Aran neina
is
admitting that Emptiness is difficult
and he says why the heck do you think
that Buddha sat there without saying
anything for seven weeks you know he was
afraid not only no one would understand
he was afraid they would
misunderstand so he thought it was
better not to talk about it and that's
that's very deep so here's the here's
the greatest emptiness explainer in
history the second Buddha
araj and then he's like why do you think
Lord Buddha hesitated to teach you know
if it wasn't dangerous if it wasn't easy
to misunderstand why do you think Lord
Buddha refused to teach and he he puts
it uh in an interesting way he says uh
Tu the the holy heart theol heart of the
Buddha was hesitant to speak he says the
holy heart of the Buddha was hesitant to
speak because he was afraid people would
misunderstand and especially they'd say
oh everything's empty so I can do what I
want or I don't have to be nice to
people or I can I can you know
everything's empty I I can do anything
he was afraid that people would think
that and that's why he refused to teach
originally okay who's he's talking to a
guy like that
that what's he saying to the other guy
you're the reason why Buddha didn't
talk okay understand TR really he's like
you're the you're people like you is why
Buddha didn't talk you okay maybe he's
finally
criticizing okay
[Music]
uh now if I had to choose one verse out
of the four 40 verses of this chapter
which is called an examination of the
four higher truth if I had to choose the
most famous
verse uh it's this next one okay and
because we my teacher my Sanskrit
teacher was uh he was into
statistics he he he he he he kept manual
paper notes of how many times a word was
mentioned in a book
he kept count and uh and it's kind of a
statistical approach
to the study of the classics okay and I
was brought up on that
partly and when I write an introduction
to the mixnuts books I like to be able
to
say clearly what's the gous most famous
birth you know which one was used in the
last two 2,000 years the most what's the
top 10 what's the biggest hit of all
time you know this is one of them okay
and and you can check I do this I I do
weird things like this where was I I was
doing it in
Peru in Lima in a coffee shop in with
Stanley NS or I forget for narina and uh
this is one of the most famous okay this
is this is in the top 10 okay uh
everything is right with anything for
which Emptiness is right if emptiness
fits something everything will fit if
emptiness doesn't fit something then
nothing will fit that thing
okay it's like genes and I'm not going
to explain the same example I usually do
but it's like a pair of jeans like okay
they will fit if there's emptiness and
they won't fit if there's no emptiness
okay and this is very very
famous if it's empty everything's good
if it's not empty
disaster okay nothing works without
emptiness okay don't think that
emptiness means nothing works emptiness
means everything works if it's not empty
it won't work okay let's talk
pens let's talk pens I don't
have okay simple
demonstration okay and and 100% correct
and if you don't think so then I built a
billion dooll business by
accident which is possible but
unlikely okay
so what's the emptiness of what's the
dependent origination of this pen what
does it really mean to say all things
depend on something else what ises it
really
mean it just means it's coming from
seeds in your mind that's all you know I
read these long long sociology books I I
read a book about Buddhism it means
we're all connected you know blah blah
it's not what it means okay dependent
origination just
means uh
everything's coming from seeds in your
mind that's all simple and that comes
from how you treat other people
therefore everything is coming from how
you treat other people that's all zero
that's all that's all that's dependent
origination you know don't don't worry
about everything else okay pen is
coming did this pen come of from a
factory in Japan or did this pen come
from gishi Michael's
mind came from the seeds in your mind
okay uh uh the factory also came from
the seat of my mind that's how the
factory can make anyway okay uh and
that's the
dependent so what's the emptiness of the
P for
$1,000 and you cannot raise your hand
before I ask the
question for
$1,000 you gotta find the money honey
okay for ,000
uh what's a good way to teach emptiness
to a crowd of
people ask them to use the finger to
point anything which hand
please left
hand Diamond way hidden
Buddhism that's the okay for the rest of
your life if you want to teach emptiness
okay say everybody raise your left hand
Point your finger okay this finger okay
don't use the other finger especially
especially in Arizona they all got
guns uh okay point to one thing in this
room that does not come from the seeds
in your mind then you you got to make it
dramatic okay you can't just say haha
you got to
go and then don't forget you got to do
then you gotta kind of do this okay I
mean you can't just go like that you
gota and that's emptiness that's all
that's perfect emptiness teaching okay
that's a perfect emptiness teaching oh
do you understand yes then why did you
get upset at your husband
yesterday okay there's an old diamond
mountain joke which I'll tell you again
because old men forget which jokes
they've told and which jokes they didn't
tell there was a we just finished that
topic at diam Mountain I don't know like
10 years ago okay nobody's here who was
in that group and uh one person was
visit you know they were a new person
and they came in just after that lecture
they came in and they're like they were
always complaining about diamond
mountain you know and uh it was hard we
didn't have anything you know and
they're always complaining and they come
in and we said are you okay and and they
say I'm surrounded by
idiots and we were in a circle around
this person and and we're
like and then we all
[Laughter]
go get it yeah meaning we come from
you okay all right and that there's no
more emptiness than that okay okay that
song if things are empty everything
works if things are not empty nothing
works he said the opposite at the
beginning of the chapter okay and he
took the most important thing the four
truths the first teaching of Lord Buddha
and he he said emptiness cancels the
four truths and we say no if the four
truths have emptiness they work and if
it don't if they don't have EMP
they don't work okay got it this verse
is very very famous okay if you
sometimes you should memorize a verse if
you want to learn Sanskrit there's no
more clear and simple and meaningful
Sanskrit than this book this verse and
and
I I'll put the by the way I'm using a
commentary by chony Lama doid who lived
300 years ago
and some day I'll translate it if I ever
have time and other people don't ask
[Music]
me so okay
uh 6.
6.2 we are GNA do q& a
in 12 minutes Tim am I
right yeah okay all right
next next
one I think it's uh yeah 18 versus this
is Verse 18 by the way if you did a
statistical analysis this is a popular
chapter in the last 2,000 years okay
it's like a hit
song and and by the way if anyone asks
you what is m way mean what does maaka
mean okay this is the answer okay who
who's better than the to say what is the
middle way okay so this is the most this
is a super famous verse where Aran thear
explains what is the middle way okay
what is middle way and he says the thing
we call dependence what's dependence
means everything's coming from seeds in
your mind when I say dependent
origination blah blah I hate that
word uh when I say dependence I hate
that one okay it just means stuff is
coming from seeds in your mind from how
you treat other people that's dependent
origination that's all okay that is
emptiness who
said the go okay he should know okay
that is is it technically
emptiness no emptiness is a NE
negative uh dependence is a positive
thing okay tell me the way things work
they come from seeds in your mind tell
me the way things don't work they don't
not come from sin human okay got it
emptiness is always something
missing okay and then uh dependent
origination is always something's there
therefore they cannot be the same thing
they can technically logically they
cannot be the same thing one is an
absence one is a presence they cannot be
the same
thing then he says uh you want to know
what dependence which is Emptiness is is
the fact that things are labeled
label is a middleway expression for
created from season your mind okay is
this a pen yes is it labeled a pen yes
is that because we call it a pen no
okay label normally means a name that
you put on a like a price tag you put on
some bread or something like that okay
but it that's not what it means in in
middle way it means comes from your
seeds labeled by your mind and that
labeling is always done with mental
pictures the the seed opens in your mind
and a mental picture comes out and it it
it it covers this I love to use the
image
of ice cream two balls of vanilla gelato
ice cream at Moscato
restaurant and then you say put on the
chocolate sauce mixed with
the heavy
coffee and and that the imagees cover
the stick like that and then it becomes
a pen okay so when they say say name
only it means picture only okay when
they say labeled it means labeled with
pictures
okay and that's why a dog can look at it
and
say I'd like to chew on it okay by the
way the dog thing sounds easy it sounds
too simple it sounds like gu trying to
be easy you know I'm
not okay if a dog
sees something else if a dog wants to
chew on this instead of write a poem
with this it proves The Emptiness of the
pen and you don't need 2,000 years of
the Classic's
house okay seriously okay if a dog sees
something
different it proves it has emptiness
that's all so simple so simple and no
one in the universe can argue you no one
can say no a dog sees it as a pen they
just
forgot yeah you know no you can't say
that if a dog really sees something else
which is proven by how they react they
chew they don't write they must be
seeing something different and that
proves the thing is empty that's all you
don't need anything else okay the fact
that a dog doesn't see a pen is proof of
Buddhism
it's proof that Buddhism is is correct
and it's proof that you cannot die if
you understand
Buddhism okay it's proof okay the dog
thing is proof and and no one can no
one's ever tried no one ever succeeded
to proof to me it wasn't proof there was
a guy in Florida who
tried got to be from
Florida I'm not I'm not
say there was a funny thing something
funny happened there recently anyway I'm
not going to talk about politics okay uh
and the fact that the the fact that the
pen is coming from your seeds what's the
final line
here that is the middle way okay don't
ask me what's Mima Mika by the way
either one is correct don't ask me don't
ask me what's middle way that is the
middle we things are halfway between
dependence and
emptiness okay and that's the middle way
and that's the highest School of
Buddhism okay there's nothing higher
than thatone that's also the Buddhism
which is used for Tantra okay Diamond
way depends on Ma okay Diamond way is a
majima schol okay
cool all
right we got four more minutes of
[Music]
okay okay now okay these great Buddhist
uh thinkers they're also cute they do
cute stuff I think he play Jimmy
Hendricks if he was
here uh so someone has to tell me next
verse why is this cute
go ahead I'm not offering money you can
just
yell yeah yeah he's using the opponent's
logic against the opponent which is
where Neal always ends up okay it's it's
similar to a wife or a husband okay so
he's like
Listen by the way he uses exactly the
same Sanskrit words as the opponent used
in the first line and then he comes back
with you know what honey
bunny if things are not empty then the
Fortress are
wrong because the other guy started out
the whole chapter he said if things are
empty then the for trth are wrong and
then the G says we're on verse 20 we're
halfway through the chapter and he goes
you know
what when I think about it if things
aren't empty the for truth are wrong and
the guy's like oh you know he's using
the same words he's using the same
language against the guy you know by by
this time he's explained about mental
seeds and he's explained about the pen
and then he says you know what when I
think about it if things are the way you
say then there's no hard truth and by
the way I did not add to the class the
whole next series of arguments which is
if there's no emptiness there's no four
high CHS and you cannot relate to those
four higher CHS and you cannot get the
results of those four Cho and you know
and he goes through the whole
thing if if things are not empty we have
a
problem
okay okay that's cute and that's typical
thear let me see how my my time's doing
I think I
got uh let's finish this I know it's QA
is coming up right away
uh let's finish I'm going to try to stay
on track because we have a job we're
going to finish the
whole
book okay
[Music]
um okay good next
picture
Gibson he's
like can you read the to
then are
you uh
[Music]
good
okay uh by the way
um yeah
I I we have typed in the uh Classics
using Roman letters why didn't we use
Chinese characters why didn't we
use Hebrew characters you know uh at the
time we started the project in
1983 at 80 887 83 at Pine Hall uh all
computers in the world were based on ASI
characters and they were using Roman
characters so you know we started
inputting the data in Roman
characters and uh so I might there's one
weakness of the shensong tower classes
is that this the translators are not
used to
reading wood carving and it's hard to
read a wood carving the wood carving is
there's a problem with wood there's
knots in Wood then they twist the
letters they they twist the letters to
fit the grain of the wood therefore it's
difficult to OCR that's why we have
people typing we don't do optical
character recognition the optical
character recognition makes as many
mistakes as a typist who just drank a
lot of
malti okay it's the same same result
okay so anyway here you can see the
problem now for zero
Gibson who
Master Shanti DEA yeah good okay this is
Master Shanti dea's nickname and it
means lazy good for nothing
slob okay so if you want to pay a high
compliment to your friends you can say
you remind me of Shanti
DEA you're just a
buur because uh the people in his
Monastery thought that he was a lazy no
good guy but actually he was busy riding
at home and he couldn't do all the other
activities that people were
expecting and uh then he wrote The Great
one of the greatest books ever written
and I was
very hesitant to take it out of the
requirements the prerequisites but I did
okay because it's three courses 10 11 12
right so I was very hesitant to take it
out of the but anyway otherwise take you
too long son buaku is the master of bodh
Sala activities no one wrote a greater
book about the
lifestyle of aodh sappa than busu okay
of Shanti de by the way in the ancient
carvings they call him busu it's
interesting it's like a pride he's proud
you call me Mr lazy I am hone
I'm so lazy you have no idea you know
all his work was secret you know and
anyway uh so Ari in giner says if things
are the way you want them to be and if
things are not empty then there's no
Buddha and then there's
no body sa
Char yeah there's no buod Sapp's way of
life according to you if he's really
attacking the guy okay first he said
yeah you're right there's no for truth
if things are not empty and then he says
and by the way there's no three jewels
if things are not empty because there's
no Buddha if things are not empty and
that you can't get to be a Buddha
because there's
no six Perfections according to you got
it okay so at this point AR neina is
criticizing the other guy according to
you there six Perfections are out the
window we don't need them and Shanti DEA
was just I don't know maybe he was Buu
wasting his time okay got it so now when
you see this picture you will
remember without emptiness nobody
suffers forget three Jews nobody suffers
okay nobody could be a bu stoper without
emptiness you cannot practice the
Buddhism the six Perfections if you
don't understand emptiness and it's
emptiness that makes them
perfect okay
uh then uh I think oh this is the last
one then we'll do a
Q&A ready yeah uh new books are out from
Rosa V grian you should thank her you
should say
hi
uh so she's doing two cool things she's
uh in charge of publishing all the
mixnut translations they have done 14 or
15 books now and no one in history has
done that for the last Shang
14400 16 yeah no one's done it for 1600
for 600 years
right
1410 1400 yeah no one's done what we're
doing in 600 years okay and uh it's
amazing and a lot of it is Rosa so when
you see her you should thank her uh but
she's been working really hard she did
two cool
things
uh so some of my early books I did with
a big publisher in New York and they
have the copyright that I cannot I
cannot print the book she bought the
copyright from them or she negotiated so
we have the right to print a certain
number of my own book uh thank you so
much and because they still make money
off it and they don't want to give us
the right but we bought the right so she
did a cool thing and a couple of these
books are 25th anniversary books okay so
it's 25 years since I wrote The Garden
which is about an amazing
Angel and it's uh
sorry and it's about uh 20 it's 30 years
since I translated uh the principal
teachings of Buddhism and uh the yoga
Sut anyway we got permission to
republish them you can and get the books
now so there's a QR code do you know
what to do with a QR
code yeah and then uh we have come out
with a hardback edition of emptiness
meditations which is venerable udala
bets Greer's
translation and it's the best emptiness
meditation book you can buy and it
includes all of the details of proper
meditation technique so even if you
don't want to read The Emptiness part
the second half is how to meditate and
it's
kamila's uh instructions on how to
meditate so anyway those books are Rel
are available I'm not doing an
advertisement I'm pointing out something
uh the guardi says at the end here and
by the way we just finished this chapter
okay he
says uh if you really understand
emptiness you understand
sees okay if you're an emptiness Master
you understand
sees and there came to be out of that
statement there came to be a famous
famous uh genre of literature a whole
kind of literature where people sing
Love love songs to Lord Buddha for
teaching
dependence you know you're so beautiful
you taught seeds you know like you
taught emptiness in seeds so this whole
theme of his of this U songs and there's
a whole there's a whole collection of
songs that that are to Lord Buddha and
they're like you are so beautiful
because you taught empty is through
seeds and the important part is through
SE and the most beautiful of those songs
is called tendel TOA which means a
praise of Lord Buddha for teaching
emptiness in the form of
seeds and uh that was there's a
translation of that and a
commentary is just did you you're going
to finish it
tomorrow uh Gibson's finishing tomorrow
okay you can be there all
right he's on the last couple sentences
we keep slowing down just before we get
to the end it's very similar to asking
your husband to clean the toilet uh gets
slower and slower but we're almost done
I I think we have to finish tomorrow
there's only three words left I don't
think we can stretch it out but uh but
that because this is where it comes from
this verse is where it comes from the
the last verses of this chapter is where
neist says look there's nothing sexier
than dependent
origination hugging
emptiness okay if you really understand
them you see them as a couple okay and
so he talks about that
uh okay
yeah that's enough we'll stop there okay
Q&A don't say I didn't do
Q&A uh I'll leave it up to you guys with
the
microphones first of all thank you for
teaching guys thank you for coming it's
good to see you thank you thank you
Manny Manny's uh I think he was there
when ACI started 100 years ago it feels
like it yeah um I've been think thinking
a lot about truth and the nature of
Truth lately and in particular the truth
of the law of karma which um you know
gets dangerously close to the dreaded is
the law of karma self-existent question
but I'm I'm curious especially uh with
what's going in the world on in the
world today how to think about the truth
of the law of
Karma and is it like the truth of 2+ 2
equal for and how do you relate that
to what are apparently other people's
truth and to take an extreme example
your your average
jihadist would say that the the fastest
path to Paradise is acts of heinous
violence is that true for them is there
an absolute so if you could comment on
how to think about truth and how to
define what is true it would be most
helpful
yeah cool I I'll tell what I think
of and I think what Buddhism would say
is
uh uh we call it the three test of gold
right and it took me a long time to
understand those three and I kept going
back to them again and again and again
so in the ancient
times you bought a
HX uh you would pay with corn or
something so the GU say 400 pieces of
corn you say no
390 and there wasn't any P there was no
what do you call it in China upay or Ali
pay there wasn't any Ali pay before
there was no alip pay there wasn't any
credit cards before there was no credit
cards there was no cash before there was
no cash there was no gold
coins and before there was no gold coins
there was no corn and so when you bought
a horse uh you paid for it in corn and
you agreed on how many pieces of corn
and by the way the ancient way to burn
money literally is to burn
grain and that's what the fire offering
is all about it's like I I have more
faith in the Buddha than the grocery
store I I will burn money to offer to
Buddha and I won't be able to use that
money after that I won't be able to eat
it after that that I I believe so much
in Buddha I will burn the money and
offer it that's what a fire offering is
so anyway
um people started to use pieces of gold
and then dishonest people popped up
about 10 minutes later and started
covering Le with gold and then there
came to be a thing called the three
tests of gold okay uh sear say SE
SE means burn it chain means cut snipp
it and dar means file it okay and then
they say how to how to establish truth
is the three test of gold this is
traditional
language uh goes back to horse base okay
so s
means one part of deciding whether
something is true or not is can it be
confirmed with your person direct
experience okay like and that's hard in
the case of jihad right like did you
ever kill an Infidel and then go to
heaven and you're like I don't know I
you know I haven't got that far yet so
you know that would be direct experience
so in this case it's probably not it's
not practical I guess and then there's a
second uh test which is called
chick which is to snip the gold and see
what's inside with metal metal scissors
or something like that and that refers
to confirming something with logic you
know and and and that's kind of where a
Buddhist would answer initially they say
there's a
consistency between cause and effect
when you plant a pumpkin seed you get a
pumpkin when you plant an Apple so you
get an Apple when you plant violence you
don't get happiness you know that we
would say that's illogical uh
just just objectively forget religion
forget how you brought up you know it
doesn't make sense that you would plant
a hot chili and get a banana or
something it just they're not similar so
it's illogical to say that violence
could lead to happiness okay that's
second test D What's
d d is to file it you know by the way
these are all what we call destructive
tests which are discouraged in the
diamond business you don't want to smash
a diamond to see if it's
real okay but the third test is uh to
file it and see if you hit lead and
that's called
uh that's called what do you call it uh
author you can say
authority
authority now Authority is tricky and
kind of the definition of authority is
up to now now I followed that advice and
everything was good that's the best you
can say with authority authority is a
little bit weak compared to logic you
know Authority means M gessi Michael so
far in my life the stuff he told me to
try I tried it and it worked out now
he's saying I shouldn't kill people
because I won't go to Nirvana now I
don't I can't confirm it but given his
track record given that you know
everything he told me in the past worked
out I'll take a shot you know and it's
by the way that's weak because it could
be gu you Michael fails on this last one
you know so but that's the three tests
of Golds but if you find a person who is
trustable that's why you have to spend
so
long uh choosing a spiritual teacher you
have to check check check check check
and then and then you start to follow
with they say so anyway that's what a
Buddhist would answer those are the
three
tests of Truth and if they pass those
tests then then we would say it's likely
to be true like
so cool all right now it's true that we
are having I'm having breakfast I don't
know what you're
doing uh is it do you getting so I say
it's true now you find out if I'm
telling the truth or not uh okay thank
you